Marvin Townsend Papers
Marvin Townsend Papers
1959-1970
Townsend, Marvin.
.25 linear ft.
Original cartoons and a few pieces of correspondence.
2653508
Biographical History
Marvin J. Townsend (1915- ) is an American cartoonist and commercial artist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Marvin Townsend Cartoons collection contains original artwork, correspondence, memorabilia, and published material.
Artwork contains original art -- ink and zipatone screening -- for Townsend's strips Bert (drawn for National Safety News), Foxy, Little Tommy Hawk, Poochie, and Quacker. Several of these ran in the Catholic Messenger's children's publication, Our Little Messenger. There is also a large number of unidentified panels and strips.
The bulk of Correspondence is fan mail, much of it from children regarding the strips that ran in Our Little Messenger. There are a few pieces of correspondence from clients, a few requesting original art or commenting on some aspect of a specific cartoon, and one folder from Dorothy Andrews, editor of Our Little Messenger, with a list of age-appropriate words and topics. There is also a folder of correspondence with St. John's School for the Deaf regarding Townsend's wordless strip Julie and Jack.
Memorabilia consists of a biographical sketch and a photocopy of a "Certificate of Merit" for cartooning.
Published material contains a clipping of a page of gag panels done for FTD. The book Moontoons Jokes and Riddles has been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Book, Moontoons Jokes and Riddles, sent to Rare Books for cataloging.
Subject and Genre Headings
Townsend, Marvin.; Our little messenger.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Deaf -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Dogs -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Ducks -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Extraterrestrial beings -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Indians of North America -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Outer space -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Comic books, strips, etc.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Comic strips.; Fan mail.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marvin Townsend, 1967.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Bert, circa 1959; for National Safety News (Box 1)
  - Foxy (Box 1)
  - Little Tommy Hawk (Box 1)
  - Poochie (Box 1)
  - Quacker (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous panels (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous strips (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Andrews, Dorothy, 1955; 1963; editor, Our Little Messenger (Box 1)
  - Fan mail, 1960; 1964,; 1967,; undated (Box 1)
  - St. John's School for the Deaf, 1964-1965; includes published booklet, Laugh and Learn with Julie and Jack (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-1966; undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous, 1970; undated (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Miscellaneous, 1960; 1970 (Box 1)
    See also Correspondence: St. John's School for the Deaf